All right,
it is December 18th, 2025. This is going
to be a brief 2025 review stream going
over the 72 videos of 2025.
And just to review, recap, make a kind
of concentrated, distilled final end
product, taking a quick look back,
seeing if any AI perplexity tools can
help us get another look at
the videos,
looking at anyone's comments for who's
watching live,
seeing if we have any memories, any
reflections, any trends that were
arising during the year or in
relationship with previous years
and looking towards what could be in
2026.
So let's collapse all these and we'll go
from the top.
Okay,
we'll just reorder things as we go.
There was uh well first just at the
level of the series
and the KOD page that I'm at is in the
video description if you look um our
videos our streams are sorted into
different series
and they are reflected upon here. So,
one math art stream, 35 guest streams,
that's the most general kind of oneoff.
Four quarterly roundtables, the last one
coming tomorrow.
One or stream, two model streams, three
math streams, this review stream, 10
textbook groups, [snorts]
three very long videos for the applied
active inference symposium, and 12
active inference streams with some sort
of coding and various works. So let's
just jump in. In the first
we have feedback welcome with Andrew
Penland. And let's just see if
Perplexity can summarize this video.
This was a fun video
because it involved
in contrast with pretty much any other
video a a very specifically visual
component
using OBS for feedback kind of like
that.
So that's fun to uh play play with the
with the format and talk about feedback,
talk about strange loops, all these
different kinds of things that come up
in the course of math but also get
reflected on in the art.
Uh
we had three quarterly roundts so far
and the fourth one will be happening
tomorrow. These are organizational
update videos
moving from the the practice of
organizations into the theory of
organization.
or stream 9 with Manuel Hoffman was on
the value of open source software and
here is what
comes from that perplexity on feedback
welcome.
Interesting. This was just a generic,
but in other cases,
Perplexity is able to have some access
to
live streams,
but appears to have some issues.
But on this one, it came out just fine.
It's all good. We won't really work with
the perplexity. We'll just see what
reflections people manually have. Um,
this org stream was awesome. I think
it's very important to explore this
question of of the the value and the
support of open-source software. And I
think it it provides a a great starting
point for talking about how do we
evaluate the value of what is made
openly. And you can see their kind of
evaluation
uh strategies which are the norms in
economics
and uh talk about other think about
other ways to value software.
So very cool to see this kind of
pragmatism brought and to bring value to
what is often easy to dismiss as as
simply free.
In this year there were two model
streams
earlier in the year in March and April.
Model streams are intended for kind of
technical walkthroughs on generative
models. So we had model stream 17 with
the RX infer team and with Frasier
and this was a provocative
presentation about what is wrong with
active inference of course a bit of a
Hegelian approach here to then propose
their own work but it was a great
follow-on discussion and led nicely into
a lot of the ongoing work that's
happening with RX X and Fur in model
stream 18.
This was a presentation on
distributingly robust pre-energy
principle for decision-m.
Okay, I'm going to update the title in
the
production document.
Just for a context, this this KOD page
that I'm referencing is where all of the
live stream information is coordinated.
The video is open to everybody with the
link. You won't have edit access, but
that's where the protocol, the procedure
for how we schedule and do live streams
and who people have brought up to
invite, all these kinds of things. And
in this
video, they presented on their robotics
research
and about
how to deal with robustness of
decision-m when there's uncertainty
about the
robots world.
Okay,
there's of course this review stream,
strange loopy as it may be.
There were three math streams, 12, 13,
and 14.
These were some of
the most
clear
memories for me. I I always enjoyed
these mouse streams. Uh in 12.1
Ola running
uh
presented on the the elbowing stein. So
evidence lower bound is
equivalent essentially to variational
free energy. So just uh
sorry about that.
We should be back.
Um,
very nice statistical methods covering
some of these distributional update
rules and and ways to uh go back and
forth and to use these particles, inject
these particles in
as tracers on a vector field.
Mathstream 13 disco pi monoidal
categories for active inference of
interest for those who are exploring the
category theory active inference
interface and disco pi is a
programming package that helps represent
uh string diagrams. So here's a string
diagram for cooking
and
Alexi goes into string diagrams for for
active inference and uh gives some
background on category theory. Then in
math stream 14,
Jesse von
presented on his review paper a concise
mathematical description of active
inference in discrete time. So [snorts]
great concise pedagogical materials.
There were more than 10 but I guess only
10 represented here uh textbook groups.
This represented some of the closing
times probably for this cycle at least
that we are working through the 2022
active inference free energy principle
in mind, brain and behavior textbook as
we are eagerly looking towards
the fundamentals of active inference
principles, algorithms and applications.
of the free energy principle for
engineers by Sanjie Nam Jooshi coming
out in
March of next year. So we're getting
excited for that textbook group and
looking back on these textbook groups.
These are always fun there. There's
there's so much to this material and to
uh
appreciate Andrew Basha for facilitating
a bunch of the textbook group meetings
and to all the participants who show up.
Uh active imprance streams.
These were streams that that I
expose ways to show what I'm working on
often in the active inference or in the
meta research or in the tool development
space. And
the year began with some plain text
exploration.
April agents bring May simulations that
was exploring some different agentic
systems. the more LLM coordinationbased
open manis as well as the probabilistic
generative models with RX infer
cerebrum began a thread related to
linguistics and basian approaches to
language noorg as a organizational agent
coordination
framework
generalized notation notation the
following
three and 14 and this was moving through
this domain specific language for
generative models and going from plain
text to triple play. So from the
configured file into the code that's
executable the mathematical
representation diagrammatic
representation natural language
there was the golden spike moment for
multi- aent trajectory planning where I
reverse engineered the example of
multi-agent trajectory into this
configurable format and then forward
engineered the configuration and we met
in the middle had a golden spike moment
and that is hopefully of interest to
people who who want to see that kind of
industrial grade scientific integrity
for generative models and the sound of
uncertainty which was adding some
features into the GNN package like audio
format rendering directly of generative
models not just their outputs like
listening to the configuration
start here
operational metaccientific arts and
crafts and generative education
yesterday
capped off a sort of content
development,
educational and research tool
development arc. Uh, and each of these
videos have their associated code and so
all open source.
Now we get to the most variable
which will be the symposium and the
guest stream. So the applied active
inference symposium, the fifth
one was in
November 2025. [snorts]
And here was the public program just for
reference. We had three three days live
streams,
keynote by Carl Fristen, bunch of live
streams, some more workshop
sections, and a bunch of pre-recorded
videos.
And we have the timestamp information
available for all of them. Those have
been added to the videos.
So about 40 or 50 presenters really
awesome to see and looking forward to
the next year's symposium. And then just
last section here for this video is
looking at the guest streams
and let's see here what trends might
emerge. We had rhythmic prochy self uh
active imprints for self-organizing
multilm systems a basian thermodynamic
approach to adaptation. This was very on
trend I think for 2025 looking for
similarities, differences, convergences,
synergies
with active inference, probabilistic
modeling, cognitive modeling and LLM
which was uh one of the themes of the
year.
In January, Ron Edelman presented on
cognitive experience design, designing
AI systems for trust. Also complimenting
I think another part of that trend which
is not just at the technical backend
side but also in terms of the human
computer interface, user interface side.
How how do we design how do we think
about these concepts like trust?
Matt Sims presented on slime mold and
philosophy and Matt had presented
here's the full
video table.
Matt had joined us
in October 2021
to discuss his paper
how to count biological minds. symbiosis
and the free energy principle. So
classic Dave Douglas, Steven Clet
joining as well. Uh and joined us this
year to discuss his book on slime mold
which was a a book I got the physical
version of and read. Nice,
quick, concise read.
In February, we had the group of Marie
Smith presenting on their work on human
computer interaction.
So here
and with Arun who who coordinated this
presentation.
There's so so many uh so many
interesting analyses. I think when we
look across all the videos,
which which visual representations
of
active inference of of the agent
environments do people use? What's the
rhetoric? What's the technical
justification for the different kinds of
works? What what do people bring up as
their uh
their justification? What do they
highlight as their their challenges and
their successes?
This group in particular put in a lot of
work to making the different stages of
their generative models operation very
clear. So great presentation
guest stream 90.2 with Benjamin Nelson a
intern. This was uh I was in a coffee
shop and there were some disruptions
which I guess was also sort of the theme
of the year. Um, and it was very
interesting
although all over the place and I hope
was a useful milestone and marker on
Benjamin's journey
going into May. AL Gwen and Carloo
presented on from contextuality to
social constraints and active inference
ontology for participatory realism and
social change.
Those familiar with Advil's work will
will know he always brings a very very
rich very holistic view
to to the technical elements of the work
and and extends and connects it into the
social sciences and some may remember a
different version of this image in the
2023 course on the social sciences
gueststream 100.1 palendrome
with you Kanazawa on the free energy
principle and implications for language
learning and education. This was a very
memorable stream for me. Uh partially I
think it was nighttime
could have been could have been morning
in Japan.
Use style is extremely
energetic
and dense
visual
information
that really brought together a great
number of points and connected it to
language learning and education which is
something we've all done andor are
doing. So this was a very fun and
relevant presentation
into April.
Little bit of a busier April. Guestream
101 with Mosen Jafari and Yulan Lee was
on navigating autonomous vehicles on
unmarked road with the fusionbased
motion prediction and active inference.
So this is uh getting into the
applications in robotics and autonomous
vehicles. and and smart homes.
And so uh and also to the more technical
theme of similarities and differences
with generative AI and active inference.
Here we saw the diffusion modeling and
the way that the forward and reverse
diffusion modeling could be used which
came up in some other streams.
4 9 25 2 3 squared
5 squ
with Majid Benny who we will look at his
some of his previous uh
times joining here was a great stream
with Dean
and Majid always has a lot of uh
very interesting philosophical points.
He joined. Interesting. Majid was the
first guest stream in February 2021.
A critical analysis of Marovian monism.
Very first guest stream.
Oh, total throwbacks. Total throwbacks.
And so while what's new and recent is
great, it's also really nice to look
look back at some of these older
presentations, see where things were
and
the paper
and then in
interesting
2022 did Majid. Yes,
Majid worked on
Tale of Two Architectures and then in
the of course epic Dean infused live
stream 47 series on the double play with
inactive social cognition and abduction.
The abduction thread continued to be
developed by Mjid and colleagues.
Still in April this year, we had 82.5
with Robert Warden,
a institute research fellow on computers
meaning and consciousness. And this was
part of a series by Warden.
He has now presented on seven guest
streams
that took us from the requirements
equation, threedimensional spatial
cognition, projective wave theory of
consciousness and assessment of the
brain wave hypothesis. That was last
year. And then this year in April and
October was computers meaning
consciousness, unified theory of
language and language and human nature.
This was a a a rockness roundt
discussion and uh had
a bunch of guests
in
April.
Tobias Plowman presented on the mind in
motion a systems model of real-time
cognitive transitions.
So this was
a cognitive modeling approach that
Tobias
had developed.
April Tanahhiro Tanaguchi joined for
collective predictive coding and active
inference a new perspective on emergent
communication.
And let's look at
[snorts]
He also joined
later
in guest stream 118 for co-creative
learning via Metropolis Hastings
interactions
and these were both excellent
presentations also nighttime for me also
fantastic
visually
comprehensive
technically distilled
Very nice presentations bringing
together
the fundamental, the biological, the
generative, active inference.
And
in the second of Tatahhiro's
presentations on the channel,
he talked more about
uh
extending from the collective predictive
coding
into the
Metropolis Hastings naming game and
about this sort of third option
that is neither supervised nor
unsupervised but co-creative.
And so that was very very
thoughtprovoking and is a great example
of where something can have both a
narrow technical
contribution to make as well as a
broader philosophical point. and and
Todd Herro
really spanned that gamut.
into May.
Paulo Deio
joined to discuss systematic deviation
and
presented on
a a variety of of topics from from the
chemical to the societal.
Guestream 106 was with Bangloo and
collaborators
and they had written this very large
review and synthesis paper on foundation
agents
and presented on
each of the authors presented on on
different sections giving a a really
nice almost textbook like presentation
summarizing the the state of the field
and uh great place to to learn about
agentic and multi-agentic systems.
Gestream 107, David Beno, who's one of
the IY organizers, presented on
computational psychiatry and affective
states, some of the modeling work that
their group are involved in.
Guest stream 108 with Christo K. Thomas
next generation artificial intelligence
for emergent semantic communication.
This though of course I don't play
favorites was one of the most memorable
presentations uh for me
also with with excellent dense visual
elements.
But getting into this question of
applied semantic transfer and semantic
information contents which had been a
key theme
in our learning going all the way back
to 2021
with Chris Fields at all and the
information flow in a context dependent
hierarchical basian inference and
Christo presented on this in the mobile
networks
similar Tata Herro's work in a way
regarding multi- aent semantic transfer
and just very fascinating discussion
about how
as our communication networks move from
syntax aware bandwidth like how many
bits of information can be transferred
how much how many hard drives will it
fill up into the semantics of
information transfer we get into this
real cognitive modeling setting where
we're talking about belief updating,
message passing and you could have uh
one gigabyte file that in practical
pragmatic terms doesn't provide any
information and you could have one bit
of Shannon information that provides uh
important reduction of uncertainty for a
given agent in a moment in a context. So
how do we really work with that? And
that's where active inference came into
play. And so it was a great discussion.
Alexander Heming in 109 presented on
free energy, attentional narrow
narrowing and cognitive rigidity.
This was
I think a a sort of
cousin approach to that of Tobias
in that this was a
um cognitive modeling,
mathematical and computational model
that was connected to a lot of
day-to-day
uh aspects, cognitive systems and uh is
just cool to see all these snapshots of
work that's ongoing.
In
June, Duya is Samura joined for triple
equivalence for the emergence of
biological intelligence and this was
an excellent presentation.
Takuya had joined
previously
in
in the discussions of live stream 51 on
canonical canonical neural networks
perform active inference. So
here was the double play in 2022
was
neural network
loss function and the morphism with a
variational base. And then in 2025
he he took that two to a three went into
the triple play and in the triple play
brought in not just the neural network
and the variational base but the touring
machine formulation. So that uh went
another
fantastic
visually
exciting technically sophisticated work
bringing together some of the major
continents really in in the intelligence
landscape today the the neural network
the basian and the touring. So great and
charismatic fellow
guest dream 111.1 with Gorgi Gorgif was
on modeling and predicting
self-organization in dynamic systems out
of thermodynamic equilibrium. This was a
nice long presentation from professor
Gyorg
and
uh involved a variety of theoretical and
empirical features of far from
equilibrium systems. So we had a great
broad scoping discussion
guest stream 112 with Hadiv AI on brain
like variational inference
kind of a classic postto
great
um background we see the elbow the
evidence lower bound negative free
energy coming into play
highlighting the unifying
nature of variational free energy
minimization. coming at this from more
of a statistical
families of distributions
style rather than for example the
more
um
styled
unifying
where here's more of different kinds of
cognitive phenomena,
optimal control and model evolution and
selection, whereas
Hadi made a very
clear
walkth through of variational inference
and the elbow and presented on on
this excellent statistical work
with Sergio Yakz
on basian mechanics of economic choice
computational foundations of economic
behavior. This was a great stream.
Brought together
a lot of the history and classics and
fundamentals of micro and macroeconomics
and got all the way on through the kinds
of modeling that Sergio and colleagues
are engaged in right now and I know has
developed significantly since this
presentation as well.
Guestream 114, Chris Fields, Adam
Saffron, Maxwell Ramstead, and Carl
Fristen was on the
inner screens paper. So the inner screen
paper
related to nested blankets, to quantum
active inference and reference frames,
and to awareness and consciousness. So,
as one could imagine, it brought out a
lot of fun,
thought-provoking ideas.
I remember this late July,
early August period where there was kind
of a a turn to energy and Alexi
Gladstone presented on energy based
transformers are scalable learners and
thinkers
and this was kind of like
bringing together
energy based models and transforming
formers and was a a very
sparse, concise, clear, relevant
presentation
that is uh definitely important for
those who are looking at energy based
models and about
what where where transformers can can go
from here. Then taking a little bit more
of a physical material perspective, Max
Schaer presented on solving the compute
crisis with physics-based AS6. Those are
application specific integrated
computers. And Max was first author on
this review and perspective piece. So
basically he took us through the
paper that he wrote with colleagues
and
for
those interested in unconventional and
and conventional computing. It was a a
great paper and obviously with with
critical
economic and pragmatic relevance
[snorts]
going into guest stream 117, Robert
Stamps presented on active inference and
artificial spin ice control processes
and state selection. Here's Vladimir and
Robert was presenting on the nanomagnet
so material substrate and how predictive
coding was being implemented on this
material nanomagnetic
substrate.
118 was Todd Herro's second talk
guestream 119 with Nick Chader and
Robert McKay. This was another economics
presentation and this one was a little
bit more coming from the macroeconomics
side.
Still very market oriented
and some e exciting developments in
terms of understanding markets from
first principles.
Gestream 120 was with Ifidio Emanuel
and
he presented on several projects related
to temporality of cognitive systems and
um physics of of eye movement. Brought
in some consciousness topics and
so it was a fun and interesting talk.
Getting
to the last two here. Guest room 121,
Mike Wuest, conscious active inference.
This brought together some with a with
with a very provocative cover slide,
might I add,
on quantum active inference,
less from the information processing and
more from the material substrate of
quantum or
that type of area connected to the
cognitive and also the consciousness
aspects.
Warden guest room 122 was with Andrea H
and she presented on
wayfinding
radical relation scaling without
hierarchies models without the meat
great neuroscience informed philosophy
and and always a
good experience to listen and learn from
how she's thinking through these things.
Warden again
on 115
was Marcelo Guzman who presented on
learning in physical networks. So this
one I would say was a great cousin of
Robert Stamps in terms of the
nanomagnetics. And here's another
example of using physical unconventional
computing substrates and big discussion
topics around well okay what are the
areas that they can hot swap in? What
are kinds of cognitive or computational
functions that these unconventional
substrates can immediately be used for?
And how do we program? How do we work
with them? How do we model them?
Guestream 124, Ty Roachford, who
presented on PCT and FE and discussed
some of his work in comparing and
holding up active inference alongside
the perceptual control theory kinds of
models and connecting them with category
theory. And even just yesterday
uh Martin Na and Osman presenting on
from Charles Darwin's root brain to
Nicola Tesla's 6G worldbrain and XAI
native 6G networks
similar to Christo Thomas's presentation
in the focus on telecommunication
networks with a few different
flavors brought in that was very
interesting and a and a great power
outage disruption.
So
if anyone has a comment, write it.
Otherwise, that will basically end it.
Just wanted to touch upon each of them.
Show one last kind of distilled artifact
of what happened in this year and look
towards next year. So if you have a
idea, get in contact, leave a comment
and hope these were epistemic andor
pragmatic for you. Thanks for watching,
for participating along, and see you
next time.